Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף Daf ס״ד. Samech-Daled. We're going
to pick up on the bottom of ס״ג עמוד ב׳. Samech-Gimmel Amud
Bet. We are in the middle of discussing the issue of וסתות
Vestot or properly pronounced וסתות, Vestot,
and we discussed a lot yesterday the issue about וסת הגוף, Veset
Haguf, bodily experiences that indicate that a woman's about to get her
period. And then we moved into the וסת הימים Veset Hayamim when
there's an issue about a certain cycle of days and how those
were seen as somewhat less predictive, interestingly. On the one hand, a
וסת הגוף Veset Haguf might require fewer than three days, in the
end we say three days, but I mean three repetitions. And number
two is a וסת הגוף Veset Haguf was seen as more precise
whereas וסת הימים, Veset Hayamim, you have to there's no sex the
entire day unit either daytime or nighttime in which a woman is
expected to get her period. Let's take a look now at the
next משנה Mishnah which continues this conversation of וסת הימים, Veset Hayamim,
very bottom of ס״ג עמוד ב׳. Samech-Gimmel Amud Bet.
היתה למודה להיות רואה יום ט״ו. Haitah lemudah lihyot roah yom Tet-Vav.
So a woman regularly saw on day 15.
And I'll just remind you that seems obviously like a very short
cycle. So there are two issues here. One is the גמרא Gemara
earlier said that it meant 15 from her going to the מקוה
Mikvah which would be the 22-day cycle which is more reasonable. The
other which we'll discuss when we get to the גמרא Gemara is
that we're not talking actually about the length of the cycle but
we're talking about which day of the month she would always see
on the 15th day of the month. Okay, so we'll hold off
on that in a minute, that'll come up in the גמרא, Gemara,
but for now let's just talk about that. She would have a
15-day or let's say
22-day cycle. ושינתה להיות רואה ליום כ׳. Veshintah lihyot roah leyom Chaf.
And then one month her cycle switched to 20 days or if
we read it the way the גמרא Gemara did 27 days. Okay,
so she this month it was different. זה וזה אסורין, Ze vaze
asurin, come next month she can't have sex either on day 15
or on day 20. Because day 15 because that's the established cycle,
it's something that she's established three times and therefore until it is
uprooted three times until it's switched three times we assume that that
remains in place. One switch isn't enough to say it's changed. On
the other hand, because most recently she saw on day 20 we're
concerned that that might be a new cycle that's establishing itself. So
for this coming month we have to be concerned that the still
the long-term established cycle might still be present day 15 or maybe
if she didn't see on day 15 maybe it's an indication, you
know, maybe that the new cycle is asserting itself so she has
to also not have sex on day 20. In the interim days
she is allowed to have sex.
So let's say 15, 20 and back to 15, she doesn't have
to worry the next time about 20?
Correct. Correct, once she goes back to the established cycle she does
not have to be concerned about what has happened, you know, about
the variation. And the basic rule is a cycle is established three
times, an established cycle is uprooted when it's switched three times, let's
say it went through three times in a row, and when something
happens once or twice then you worry about it for the next
month, but if the next month once it doesn't happen then you
stop worrying about it, it's uprooted after just one time that it's
off. Okay, so three times it needs three times to be uprooted,
once or twice you're concerned about it for the next month but
you stop worrying about it, it's uprooted after just one time that
it's off. Okay.
And when you say returning to an original cycle, does that also
require another three times?
No, all that is that you sort of don't that cycle is
always present, meaning even when you're worrying for the new one you're
still always still worrying for the old one. So as soon as
you stop worrying for the new one then the old one never
has gone away.
And does this only apply only if the new one doesn't establish
itself three times?
Yes, once the new one establishes itself three times it replaces the
old one, exactly.
What about the Hebrew month?
Well, yeah, for now the Hebrew month when we get to the
month, now we're assuming length of cycle, we'll get to the month
issue in a minute. I understand, I'll talk about that in a
minute in the גמרא. Gemara. For now let's assume we're talking about
length of cycle. Okay. Now שינתה פעמיים
ליום כ׳, Shintah paamayim leyom Chaf,
so two months running she saw on day 20, not on day
15, so it still seems like it's really that's what's about to
assert itself but still it's only twice not three times. Still זה
וזה אסורין, Ze vaze asurin, come to the third month she has
to be concerned about both day 15 and day 20. שלש פעמים
ליום כ׳, Shalosh paamayim leyom Chaf,
now if it's three times day 20 הותרה ט״ו, Hutrah Tet-Vav, the
15th day becomes permitted, it no longer is a seem to be
that cycle has been overridden. וקבעה לה ליום כ׳, Vekaveah lah leyom
Chaf,
and day 20 now has taken its place. However if you had
for example 20, 20, 19, 20, right, it needs to be three
times in a row. So if she had a cycle of 15
and the next four months was 20, 20, 19, 20, then she
still has her established cycle of 15 and the next month she's
concerned about 15 and 20. You're always concerned about your established cycle
plus the most recent month if the most recent month was off
cycle. Okay. שאין אשה קובעת לה וסת עד שתקבענה שלש פעמים, She-ein
ishah kovaat lah veset ad she-tikbaenah shalosh paamayim,
a woman does not establish a וסת Veset unless she establishes it
three times consecutively. ואינה מטהרת מן הוסת עד שתיעקר ממנה שלש פעמים,
Ve-einah mitaharet min haveset ad she-teaker mimennah shalosh paamayim,
and she does not become pure from a וסת, Veset, meaning the
וסת Veset does not become uprooted and no longer relevant until it
is uprooted three times. unless it's uprooted three times consecutively. I will
say something to think about as we learn the גמרא Gemara and
becomes an interesting discussion in the ראשונים. Rishonim. What does it mean
to be uprooted three times? Let's say for example a woman had
a cycle of 15 days, and the next three days she saw
actually the example I just gave 20, 20, 19. So for three
months running she didn't see on day 15. Is that uprooted three
times? Or does it have to be replaced by something else? But
replaced by another cycle? Okay? So that is not clear because תעקר
ממנה ג' פעמים te'aker mimennah gimel pe'amim sounds like the first thing's
enough. It doesn't say until it's replaced by something of three times.
It says until three times goes and it doesn't happen. Okay, but
that is something to be thinking about as we approach the גמרא.
Gemara. Yes?
With birth control, cycle times can be controlled. Yes. So would this—I
presume this wouldn't apply?
No.
We discussed yesterday that the general approach to birth control, first of
all, is that as long as the—I just actually had a שייכות
shayachus about the sus-p... as long as the woman is on the
active pill and, you know, she doesn't have—she doesn't have spotting, because
lots of times women when they begin a pill or whatever they,
you know, they have spotting. But if she's once she's on an
active pill which she's not experiencing breakthrough bleeding, then certainly for the
time she's on the pill, she's מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim. So if
one month she's on the pill for a month and the next
time she's on it for three months, first of all for the
time she's on the active pill she's מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim and
that's number one. Number two is her cycle would be defined not
by the spacing of days, because as you say that is artificially
manipulated and that's not really the causal effect of the bleeding, and
her cycle would be determined, her וסת veset would be determined based
on the period of time after she goes off the active pill
that until which she bleeds. Now if there's some variation there you
have to figure out how to handle it. But if she regularly
starts bleeding 24 hours after the active—she goes off the active pill,
then that becomes her וסת. veset. Exactly. I have a question.
What? If she's מסולקת דמים? mesuleket damim? When she's pregnant she's מסולקת
דמים. mesuleket damim. Then she starts—when she's pregnant she doesn't worry about
it during the pregnancy and afterwards, right, then once she starts bleeding,
she doesn't worry until she actually gets her first period. Once she
gets her first period, then if she had a וסת קבוע, veset
kavua, it sort of like reasserts itself. If she had a וסת
שאינו קבוע, veset she'eino kavua, then she starts all over again.
Let's say her cycle is now 17, 18, 19, 20? Does she
have to worry the next time about 21?
All right, so that's the first case of the גמרא. Gemara. Yes,
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Top of ס"ד ע"א.
Samekh-Dalet Amud Aleph. איתמר. Itmar. ראתה יום חמשה עשר לחודש זה, Ra'atah
yom hamishah asar le-chodesh zeh, she saw day 15 on one month.
ט"ז לחודש זה, Tet-Zayin le-chodesh zeh, 16 on the next month. י"ז
לחודש זה, Yud-Zayin le-chodesh zeh, 17 on the next month. So it's
three times, but only—and with a plus-one pattern, but only two of
the months exhibited the plus-one pattern. The first month was just 15.
16, 16, 17. So you had three months, usually we need three,
but of those only two exhibited the plus-one pattern. Is that considered
established three times with a plus-one? So רב אמר קבעה לה וסת
לדילוג. Rav amar kave'ah lah veset le-dilug. Yes, she's now established a
period that every month it's going to be one more day than
the previous one. ושמואל אמר עד שתשלש בדילוג. U-Shmuel amar ad she-teshaleish
be-dilug. No, she had three times but she didn't have three times
where it was a plus-one. So therefore she has not yet had
an established וסת veset until she has a fourth time so that
she can say for three consecutive months she saw one month more
than the previous month. Okay, so that's the question. You had three
times, they all combined they exhibited a particular characteristic, but that characteristic
was not exhibited three times. Does that work or not? That's the
debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. Now before we get to
discuss proving the debate, I'll mention two things. First is just an
interesting footnote question, which is what happens when it gets so much
that it's—that you're at the end of the month? So okay, next
month 17, next month 18, next month 19, next month 20, eventually
next month 30 and then next month 31? So maybe we assume
that it goes back to the beginning, I don't know, the גמרא
Gemara never spells that out.
Why what's the significance of the month
of the month?
That's the next point. Okay, the first question is just an interesting
thing what happens when it, you know, when it gets too long.
I don't know what the answer is, the גמרא Gemara never gets
that far.
The other point is—does it—does it be to the—unlike—unlikely to occur.
I understand it's a theoretical question, but I'm just saying what is
that theoretical question?
Now, the next—relative to the—to the hormonal pills, it can extend as
long as you want.
Right. No, no, but here—so if it
is, if we're talking about, if we're talking about gaps of time,
then theoretically you could say okay a 15-day gap, a 16, a
17, a 100-day gap, 101-day gap. That's if it's a gap of
time. But—so that's—but I said specifically because the language of the גמרא
Gemara was לחודש זה, le-chodesh zeh, of this month. And the reason
I said that was not only the language of the גמרא, Gemara,
but as תוספות Tosafot points out that's actually necessary for the discussion.
Because if you're talking about gaps, then you always need one other
to see one more time in order to create the endpoints. Right?
So actually, meaning you would need to see four times if we're
talking about gaps. You see this time, then 15 days later, now
you've seen twice. Then 16 days later, then 17 days later, so
now you've only seen three times, right, you've seen four times. So
the גמרא Gemara discusses it very much as though you saw three...
Now you could say, okay, it really means we're taking the starting
point for granted and it means the next three. That's all possible,
but the simple sense of this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is that it's
actually seeing the day of the month and we're not talking about
a cycle of gaps which requires one extra point for the endpoint,
we're actually talking about when in the month. Which raises the question
that תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says, which is: what does this have to
do with when it occurs in the Hebrew month? So if you
take a look at תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says,
first he points out you need an extra point, and then the
last line of the wide lines, like four lines down in תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafot*, he says right before where the columns sort of right
where the lines get narrow, אפילו שאחד מלא ואחד חסר *Afilu she-echad
malei ve-echad chaser*, even if the months vary in terms of length,
ואין הימים שבין ראייה re'iah, לראייה שווים *ve-ein hayamim shebein reiah lereiah
shavim*, and the gap is not the same, מכל מקום קביעות החודש
גרם *mikol makom keviut hachodesh garam*, and
when the ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh, *Rosh Chodesh* is, that determined, והיכא
דבראשונה אין לה שיעור בחודש והשניה נראית בדילוג מן הימים והפעם השלישית
כראשונה *ve-heicha de-varishonah ein lah shiur bachodesh ve-hashniyah nireit bedilug min hayamim
ve-hapaam hashlishit ke-rishonah*.
Okay, so now תוספות *Tosafot* says, yeah, I understand that the gaps
aren't the same, but still the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes there could
be something called a וסת החודש Vesess Hachodesh *veset hachodesh*, a וסת
vesess *veset* based on how many days from ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
*Rosh Chodesh*. Now, the ראשונים Rishonim, *Rishonim* after תוספות *Tosafot* really get
a little bothered by this and they say: how is this possible?
What does this have to do with when the month is established,
when this woman is going to see? So the רא"ה *Ra'ah*, who
was a student of the רמב"ן *Ramban* and often said interesting things,
said: you know what? You're right. When the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
ראש חודש chodesh *Rosh Chodesh*, it doesn't mean to the, it doesn't
mean the month. It means, it means, well, it says לחודש *lechodesh*.
Anyway, it doesn't mean based on the actual month, it means based
on the מולד *molad*. So actually based on the moon. So what
it means is 15 days from the new moon, whenever that might
happen to be, 16 days from the new moon. So it might
be connected to ראש חודש chodesh *Rosh Chodesh*, it might not, but
it actually means, and that gets to what David said and actually
there has been scientific studies, I mean this isn't a surprise, but
there has been very established scientific evidence about women whose menstrual period
is very much in sync with the lunar cycles. So that's a
very nice read, but it's not literally the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* of
חודש chodesh. *chodesh*. The other response is that of the רשב"א *Rashba*
who basically says like תוספות *Tosafot*, you know what? We have to
believe that something, if, if basing creates this day as the month,
as the new moon, as ראש חודש chodesh *Rosh Chodesh*, that could
also have a metaphysical physical impact on people's bodies, and אין הכי
נמי *ein hachi nami*, you could have a cycle according to the
חודש chodesh *chodesh* even if it's not linked to the lunar cycle.
I have had somebody tell, people tell me, again I'm always skeptical,
but I definitely have had people tell me, oh no, I taught
a כלה kallah *kallah* class and there was a woman who said
she always gets it on ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* no matter what
the month is. I said okay, fine, but anyway, that is a,
now there becomes I should say three primary וסתות vestos,
*vestot* in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. There's וסת הגוף veset haguf, *veset
haguf*, which is you know like cramps and whatever, there's וסת הימים
veset hayamim *veset hayamim*, which is, which is a cycle which is
based on you know period of days, gaps, or whatever, length of
the period, and there's וסת החודש vesset hachodesh, *veset hachodesh*, which is
when it occurs within the Hebrew month and the gap is independent
of the question about the gaps of time. Yes, Josh.
This could easily be explained as וסת הימים vesset hayamim *veset hayamim*
if you have two consecutive months that are the same number of
days, which happens frequently in the calendar, this is just a woman
who has a constant gap cycle of 30 days or 31 days.
Well, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is dealing it over four periods
anyway. You know what I mean? Because 15, 16, 17, so you'd
have to assume all the months have the same time. The גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is using like a type of a shorthand. But anyway,
yes, it's possible to get out of this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. You
could either say, like I said, it's from the מולד *molad*, or
it means that there was an extra endpoint that we weren't referring
to but implicitly we're talking about gaps and there was an endpoint.
But nevertheless, based on this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* established and we פוסקין
*poskin* this way להלכה *lehalacha* that one of the וסתות vestos *vestot*
that women have to worry about is what day of the Hebrew
month. It's the וסת vesess. *veset* that seems the least linked to
any type of predictive basis of when they're actually going to see.
Yes.
Why is the מולד *molad* make more sense than ראש חודש *Rosh
Chodesh*?
Because the מולד *molad* has to do actually when the, linked to
the lunar cycle, it's when the month actually appears. No, ראש חודש
*Rosh Chodesh* given the way the Hebrew calendar is manipulated so that
certain holidays don't fall out on certain days and whatever, and sometimes
ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* can be one or two days after the
מולד *molad*, so it's not directly linked to the lunar cycle.
Yes, Josh. I mean, could you be able to do that for
English months? If someone has a pattern like that? I mean, it's
an interesting question. I don't know.
Presumably not because it's hard enough to explain based on Hebrew months
and then they bring in some type of, you know, religious metaphysics,
I doubt they would say it for the English month. Okay, so
let's take a look now at, so that's the question. So that's
the background. But the basic question here is three times you saw
but with two jumps. Does that count or not? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this. נימא רב Rav ושמואל בפלוגתא דרבי ורבן
שמעון בן גמליאל מיפלגי *Neima Rav u-Shmuel be-flugta de-Rabbi ve-Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel mipalgei*. Maybe they're debating the famous debate which you mentioned yesterday
between רבי Rebbe *Rabbi* and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel, *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* whether a normal חזקה chazakah. *chazakah* is
two times or three times. דתניא *Detanya*, we've taught in the ברייתא
braisa, *braita*: ניסת לראשון ומת *niset lerishon vamet*,
a woman got married to a first husband and he died, ושני
ומת *vesheni vamet*, and she married a second husband and he died,
and this is a case where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* basically says
that once this is happening a
lot. That is true. It does apply to a man whose wife
is dying. It is very much seen here as the woman as
the threat or the cause. Right. I don't know if the גמרא
Gemara ever suggests that she's doing it intentionally,
but you know sort of but that something about right exactly. It
you are correct. It very much somehow right is the male perspective.
I don't know how much we
actually.
That's right.
That the right that שלה Shela was concerned. I know but Michael
is saying that שלה's Shela שלה's Shela anxiety, the תורה Torah was
expressing שלה's Shela anxiety, whether it was justified or not שלה Shela
was afraid because of that.
And clearly she was able to conceive.
Right. And clearly יהודה Yehuda didn't die as a result. Right. So
that is true. I yeah I totally agree with you Rifka that
that you know it very much it sees the woman as the
threat, it focuses on the woman not on the man absolutely.
Yeah so there's a הלכה halacha that if a baby boy's two
older brothers have had a ברית bris
and died, yeah hemophilia, they
didn't know about that then.
I don't know they could have known about it by observation.
Yeah alright so okay so anyway alright so acknowledging all of those
very serious problems, how many times does it become an issue to
worry about? So רבי says twice. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר לג׳
תינשא, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer l'gimmel tinase,
she can marry a third guy. Twice is not enough to worry.
לד׳ לא תינשא, l'arba lo tinase, not the fourth guy. Especially you
have to imagine, Rifka, that if they were marrying very young women,
so it's not so unlikely that the man dies and the woman
survives depending on what the age gap is, you know, although on
the other hand, although on the other
hand, there was a high rate of death during childbirth. So anyway
alright so anyway that is the classic debate
of two times or three times what establishes a חזקה. So maybe
that's what's going on here. Right. So גמרא Gemara says לא, lo,
no that doesn't
have to be the debate. דכולי עלמא כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל, d'chulei
alma k'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, everybody holds like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל,
which is generally our assumption, you need three times, which is what
we said yesterday. Although yesterday we also mentioned the possibility once or
twice.
In the end, the dominant position
of the משנה Mishna was three times. So in principle we all
agree three times. So what's the debate here? בהא דרבה קמיפלגי, b'ha
d'Rabbah kamiflagi, this is what they debate and this certainly seems to
be the simple sense. רב סבר חמישה עשר ממניינא, Rav savar chamisha
asar miminyana, רב Rav says you count 15, 15 is one of
the three because it becomes part of a pattern and there's a
pattern that involves seeing three times even though it itself did not
exhibit the jumping aspect of the pattern. ושמואל סבר כיון דלאו אדילו
חזיתיה, u'Shmuel savar keivan d'lav adilu chazisa, no, since although it is
part of the pattern it establishes the jump, but since it itself
was not occur with a plus one occurrence, לאו ממניינא היא, lav
miminyana hee, then you cannot count it as part of the three.
It's not that there were three times a plus one occurrence. Okay.
איתיבי. asvei. So we'll ask you. הייתה למודה להיות רואה יום ט״ו,
haisa l'muda lihyos ro-a yom tes vav, our משנה... mishna... ושינתה ליום
ט״ז, v'shinsa l'yom sheis asar, not our משנה, mishna, ברייתא, braisa. similar
discussion. הייתה למודה להיות רואה יום ט״ו, haisa l'muda lihyos ro-a yom
tes vav, a woman would generally see on day 15. ושינתה ליום
ט״ז, v'shinsa l'yom sheis asar, she switched to day 16. זה וזה
אסור, zeh v'zeh asur, so 15 and 16 are both forbidden. Now
the next month, שינתה ליום י״ז, shinsa l'yom shva asar, she saw
not on 15 or 16 but on 17. So what happened? הותר
ט״ז, hutar sheis asar, 16 stopped being an issue because since it
only occurred once or twice only occurred, you stop worrying about it
after one change. So 16 stops being an issue. ונאסר חמישה עשר
ושבעה עשר, v'nesar chamisha asar u'shva asar, so the next month you
have to worry about 15 and 17. Right, you got it? 15
was established, you saw once 16, fine, next month 15 and 17.
The next month it was 17, so next month you worry about
15 and 17. שינתה ליום י״ח, shinsa l'yom shmona asar, the next
month she didn't see 15, she didn't see 17, she saw 18.
הותרו כולן ואין אסורה אלא מי״ח ואילך. hutru kularn v'ein asra ela
mishmona asar va'eilach. So now you worry about nothing, you only worry
about 18. You don't even worry about 15. Why don't you worry
about 15? Because you went three months without seeing on 15. So
this addresses the question I asked you on the משנה. Mishna. You
haven't put anything in its place, it is a simple sense of
the last line of the משנה. Mishna. You don't need to replace
it with anything as long as three months running you did not
see on 15, 15 stops being an issue. Okay, so that's a
very nice משנה Mishna ברייתא. Baraita. We certainly learned from it this
idea that if you uproot something even without replacing it, it stops
being an issue. Now what did we see though? ואין אסורה אלא
מי״ח ואילך. v'ein asra ela mishmona asar va'eilach. You only worry about
18. So now we've got a problem, right? Because it says she
saw here, you know, 15, 16, 17, 18. Okay,
so קשיא לרב. kashya l'Rav. So this is difficult to רב Rav
because you would think that you should start worrying here, you know,
even after you saw 15, 16, and 17, you should start worrying
about 18. Actually you could say why not according to שמואל? Shmuel?
You saw 18, you start worrying about 19 because anyway your pattern
with a plus-day gap. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר לך רב,
amar lach Rav, לימודא שאני. limuda shani. No, see, לימודא limuda is
different. This is a woman that had a pattern when I say
15, 16, and 17, you establish your plus-one pattern, right? That was
when a woman had no prior history or no consistent prior history.
Then 15 becomes part of the new pattern. But if a woman
every time saw on 15, then the next month when she sees
16, you don't say, oh, we've got a pattern 15, 16, 17.
15 was part of the old established pattern. It does not get
looked at in terms of determining the new pattern. Okay, so
therefore, is that clear? Meaning if you started seeing new and you
saw 15, 16, 17, you'd say, oh, look, we have an interesting
pattern here, 15, 16, 17. But if you've been seeing for years
on 15 and then this month 16, next month 17, we wouldn't
say 15, 16, 17 is the pattern. 15 is the old thing.
That was a regular 15. 16, 17, 18 is the pattern. So
רב Rav? says that's why here you needed to go all the
way up to 18 because 15 can't count towards it. I will
say that what the גמרא Gemara assumes, you know, why did it
only ask according to רב? Rav Even according to שמואל, Shmuel, right?
It says when you
once you hit 18, the next month you should be worrying about
19, right? So the גמרא Gemara has to somehow assume that the
language of משמונה עשר ואילך mishmonah asar va'eilach means now you start
worrying about the pattern established on 18, you start worrying about 19
and so on. But you know, even if you drop 15, you
still have 16, 17, and 18. That should be enough to start
worrying about 19. So the גמרא Gemara has to somehow assume that
that is what is meant by this ברייתא. Baraita Okay, so this
ברייתא Baraita wait, so
it's nothing to do with whether it's not a pattern or not,
but what you're saying is no matter what, she's worrying about 19.
So רב Rav, is saying that also. So it makes no difference
if you're saying that she had a pattern for years or she
just established a new.
No, the גמרא Gemara says she only worries starting on 18. But
it must that's what the ברייתא says. But the גמרא Gemara somehow
assumes and רש"י Rashi says this explicitly that it means from now
we've established
a new pattern. 18 is the jump-off
point, but now we're going to worry on a plus-one, next month
19, next month 20, and so on, not 18. I know it
doesn't sound that way, but that's what the גמרא Gemara assumes. So
it says this works according to שמואל Shmuel because you had four
points, 15, 16, 17, 18. You had three jumps. So that's why
starting with 18, you worry the new plus-one pattern. But according to
רב, Rav why didn't you start worrying when you hit 17? And
it says because you can't count 15 as part of the new
pattern. 15 is part of the old pattern. So really all you
have is 16, 17, 18. Okay, but again, beyond the רב Rav,
and שמואל, Shmuel, we do see a very important point that you
can uproot something without replacing it. Okay, so now let's the גמרא
Gemara continues, וקאמלי מאי קארי ליה v'ka'amlei mai ka'arei lei
and what what were you thinking in the first place? I mean,
of course, if 15 is part of an established pattern, that makes
it different and you can't count it as part of the new
pattern. So the גמרא Gemara says no, לימודא איצטריכא ליה. limuda itztarich
lei. I thought that having an established pattern of 15 would not
change this issue of, you know, of three times or four times.
I thought that it was gave me the example of an established
pattern to tell me to make a different point. What different point
was it making? מהו דתימא כיון דלימודא הוא ואיעקרתיה בתרי זימני איעקרא
ליה, ma d'teima keivan d'limuda v'akartei b'trei zimnei akrei lei, I might
have thought that you know maybe even for a woman who has
an established pattern, maybe keeping her period twice, maybe it wouldn't need
three times. קא משמע לן, kamashmalan, so he has to tell me
that no, this thing only gets uprooted with three times, not two
times. Now again, that's pretty funny. I mean, משנה Mishnah says עד
שתעקר שלש פעמים. ad she'te'akeir shalosh p'amim. So I myself would have
said the bigger חידוש chiddush is what I told you, which is
a חידוש chiddush that even with an established pattern, it's uprooted without
being replaced. It's uprooted just by being, you know, just by not
occurring. Although you could come back to me and say, what do
you mean it hasn't been replaced? It has been replaced. What's it
been replaced with? The
plus-one pattern, right? We have 16, 17, 18. We're now calling that
a new pattern. So it's even that question is not so clear.
Has 15 been sidelined because you just had three times without 15
or has it been uprooted because you had a really new pattern,
a plus-one, a 16, 17, 18 pattern? That is still not clear
even after this discussion.
Does it have to happen three times to be a new pattern?
No, 16, 17, 18 is the new pattern. Now שמואל Shmuel once,
because it's really it's because it's three times you saw within a
in a way that's predictable, you have the plus-one. שמואל Shmuel would
say it would have to be, you know, four times in order
to get the jump to occur three times. Okay, but anyway, so
you should be aware that now that we're saying we have a
new pattern, again, we don't still know the answer. Can you replace
an old pattern with nothing, or does it have to be replaced
with a new pattern?
So let's see, it goes something like, you know, plus-one and minus-one
consistently for yeah,
so you can have two you can have things like that. That's
where the פוסקים poskim start having a lot of fun when they
figure out, and let's say you have a cycle and a plus-one
like you do 16, 17, 18, 16, 17, 18, 16, 17, 18,
they start playing with all those games, which is why I think
partly why I think because this leads to these interesting types of,
you know, computation, why we get distracted and thinking everything in terms
of וסת vesess. הימים and we lose sight of what we learned
yesterday, which is וסת הגוף, Vesess Haguf, which I as I pointed
out yesterday. which I, as I pointed out yesterday, I think has
significant practical implications. I think we're well, yeah, and it's more interesting
הלכה halachically to discuss, but I think the וסת הגוף, Vesess Haguf.
it overshadows what really should be the dominant discussion which is the
וסת הגוף. vesset haguf Anyway, let's see how the גמרא Gemara continues.
מיתיבי Meseivi ask from this. ראתה יום עשרים ואחד בחודש זה ויום
עשרים ושנים בחודש זה ויום עשרים ושלש בחודש זה Raasa yom esrim
veachad bachodesh zeh veyom esrim ushnayim bachodesh zeh veyom esrim veshalosh bachodesh
zeh 21, 22, 23 קבעה לה וסת. kav'ah lah vesess. So she
has established now a וסת vesess of a plus one, a וסת
הדילוג. vesess hadilug. סירגה ליום עשרים וארבע Seirgah leyom esrim ve'arba let's
see she leapfrogged 21, 22, 24 לא קבעה לה וסת lo kav'ah
lah vesess so that's not a וסת. vesess? תיובתא דשמואל Tyuvta Deshmuel
it's a contradiction to שמואל Shmuel because you see that 21, 22,
23 establishes a וסת. vesess. אמר לך שמואל Amar lach Shmuel הכא
במאי עסקינן כגון שדילגה למפרע יום עשרים ושנתה יום עשרים ואחד. hacha
bemai askinan kegon shedilgah lemafre'a yom esrim veshinstah yom esrim veachad. No,
no, no, we're talking about a woman that had a pattern of
20 and then she saw 21, 22, 23. So even the 21
as opposed to רב, Rav I'm willing to count the 20 as
part of the pattern and therefore the 21 already was a plus
one type of a seeing. So the גמרא Gemara says, you know
what? דיקא נמי Deika nami that actually is inferred by the text.
דשבקיה ליום עשרים Deshavkeih leyom esrim because normally when we talk about
patterns we say she sees every 15 days, every 20 days, and
here we started saying 21. Why did we start saying 21? That's
an unusual way to start. So presumably ונקטיה ליום עשרים ואחד venaktih
leyom esrim ve'achad presumably it's because we're assuming she has what we
a normal example we normally talk about, she has 20 and then
this coming month she skipped to 21. שמע מינה. Shema minah. So
that's a good point, actually you're right, by starting with the 21
example it makes a lot of sense to assume that we're talking
about a woman that normally has 20, which is a normal example
we give. Not like woman's body is more likely to see an
even numbers on 20s than on 21s, but it's a normal example
that we give and therefore 21 would suggest a jump. So we
haven't resolved the debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel that if
this type of a thing occurs whether, you know, it's three times
or or four times. What we have seen is an interesting question
about using a something from an established pattern to connect it with
a new pattern. Can you do that or not? Do you say
that's not relevant, that's part of the old pattern? More significantly we
saw the question about that there's an idea of וסת vesess החודש
not explicit but implicit and developed by תוספות and ראשונים, that it's
not based on the spacing but the time of the month. And
the other question that is still unresolved is can you uproot an
old וסת vesess, by three times not make doing it, or do
you need to replace it with a new וסת? veset And even
the example we saw in the גמרא Gemara. in the end turned
out to be a repla- a replacing with a new וסת. veset
Okay, so now we continue. שאין האשה קובעת וסת עד שתקבענה שלש
פעמים. She'ein ha'ishah kova'as vesess ad shetikva'enah shalosh pe'amim. A woman doesn't
establish a וסת veset until she has it three times and doesn't
uproot until she uproots it three times. אמר רב פפא Amar Rav
Pappa לא אמרן אלא לקבוע. lo amran ela likboa. When we say
you need three times to uproot it, that's only to or to
establish it, you need three times to establish it. אבל למיחש לה
Aval lemichash lah בחדא זימנא חיישינן. bechada zimna chaishinan. One time is
enough to be concerned about it. That's all the examples we had
before, like she was regularly 15, she switched to 20, so the
next month she worries for 15 and 20. So to worry for
the immediate next month just having it once is enough, but to
establish it as a fixed pattern that needs three times. So the
גמרא Gemara says, מאי קא משמע לן? mai ka mashma lan? What
are you teaching us? תנינא Tenina it's explicit in our משנה. mishna.
היתה למודה להיות רואה יום חמשה עשר ושנתה ליום עשרים זה וזה
אסורים. Haisah lemudah lehiyos ro'ah yom chamishah asar veshinstah leyom esrim zeh
vezeh asurim. She saw 15 regularly, even one month she saw 20,
next month she worries for 20. So you see even seeing it
one month is enough to be concerned for the coming month. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, אי מהתם ei mehasam הוה אמינא hava
amina I would have thought הני מילי היכא דקיימא בתוך ימי נדתה.
hani mili heicha dekaiyma betoch yemei niddasah. That's when the shift occurred
so that this new thing that we're worried for is something that
would occur during her נדה niddah period, meaning more than 18 days
after her last ראייה, right? Because you know it's seven and 11.
So when is it something that you have to be concerned of
for the following month? If last month it occurred in a נדה
niddah period after 18 days from the last one. אבל היכא דלא
קיימא בתוך ימי נדתה Aval heicha delo kaiyma betoch yemei niddasah if
it occurred with not during the נדה niddah period, between days 8
and 18, then I would say that's totally fluke and you don't
have to worry about it, right? The whole idea of זבה zavah
is that it's not a normal menstrual period. So let's say one
month a woman saw on day one and then she saw on
day 15 not from going to the מקוה mikvah but day 15
from the last time she bled. So then I might have said
so next month you don't have to worry about day 15, that's
completely a fluke, it's within the זבה zavah period, not the נדה
niddah period. קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan therefore רב פפא Rav
Pappa said, although there was nothing about רב פפא's Rav Pappa statement
that suggested this, but רב פפא Rav Pappa reiterated that you have
to be concerned about the following month even once, that even if
that one time was during the זבה zavah period not the נדה
niddah period. Now you might remember in an earlier גמרא Gemara this
was debated, whether a seeing during a זבה zavah period, seeing three
times that doesn't establish a וסת, vesset but is it enough to
worry about it? If you see it once do you have to
worry about it? Okay, so this was an issue that was seriously
questioned in the past. The גמרא's Gemara understanding is that רב פפא's
Rav Pappa coming to say whenever you you see even once, you
always worry about it the next month, even if it's what do
you call, you know, even if it's during the זבה Zavah period.
Now I should say, though, that when a woman gets spotting during
a month, a woman could get a stain during a month and
breakthrough bleeding or whatever, and that makes her a נידה, Niddah, even
if it's coming during the period when she is obviously not expecting
her period. The following month she does not have to worry about
that stain. You would say, well isn't that רב פפא? Rav Papa?
She saw in the middle of the period whatever. So that's a
different principle, that's אין כתמים משום וסת, ein ketamim mishum veset, that
if it's a stain, even a stain that's טמא, tamei, something which
is טמא, tamei, but even if it's a stain that's טמא, tamei,
we understand that stains are not your real period, okay? And therefore,
unless it's a real heavy flow or serious flow, if it's just
a stain, then even though that could make a woman a נידה,
Niddah, it does not become an issue for וסת vesset considerations. So
רב פפא'ס Rav Papa's example would be when a woman had a
real flow and that it was but then you would establish even
though it was right real flow right even though it was in
the middle of a month even if it was like you know
within the זבה Zavah period you would worry about it for the
next period. Okay, so now we wrap this up. ואינה מטהרת מן
הוסת, ve'eina mitaheret min haveset, and she does not get rid of
her previous pattern unless it happens it gets uprooted three times in
a row. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, לא אמרן אלא דקבעה
תלתא זימני. lo amran ela dekav’ah tlata zimni. דצריכה תלתא זימני למעקרה.
ditzricha tlata zimni le'akrah. If she establishes it three times, she needs
three times to uproot it. אבל תרי זימני, aval terei zimni, if
she established it twice, בחדא זימנא מעקרא, bechada zimna me'akra, it gets
uprooted with once. I told I mentioned this before, right? Anything less
than three times, even if it's established twice in a row, if
the next month all you need is one being off and it
stops worrying about that וסת שאינה קבועה, veset she'eina kevua, about what
has not been established as a pattern. So גמרא Gemara. says, מאי
קא משמע לן? mai ka mashma lan? Again, what are you telling
me רב פפא? Rav Papa? I know this from the משנה. Mishnah.
תנינא, Tanina, אינה אשה קובעת וסת עד שתקבענה שלשה פעמים. eina isha
kova'at veset ad shetikba'ena shelosha pe'amim. It says until she establishes it
three times, and רש"י Rashi says at the end of the משנה
Mishnah and she's not מטהרת metaheret until she uproots it three times,
so it makes it clear that only an established וסת vesset requires
to be uprooted three times. Less than a three-time וסת vesset does
not require to be uprooted three times. So גמרא Gemara says no,
I would have had a very reasonable thought. מהו דתימא, mahu deteima,
I might have thought, חדא לחדא תרי לתרתי ותלתא לתלתא, chada lechada
terei letertei utlata letlata, make it all very equal. If you see
once, you have to uproot it once. If you see three times,
you have to uproot it three times. So if you see twice,
maybe you have to uproot it twice? Okay, that would have been
a reasonable assumption. So he's telling me קא משמע לן, ka mashma
lan, not that way, anything less than three only needs once to
uproot it. Is that in our משנה? Mishnah? No, it's not explicit.
Our משנה Mishnah never said that. Our משנה Mishnah just says three
times means three times. Okay, it's actually an interesting parallel by the
laws of זבה. Zavah. A woman sees, bleeds one or two days
during the זבה Zavah period, she needs one clean day, right, to
get out of it. Only when she bleeds three days and you've
established a pattern, then you need a whole seven-day period. So anything
less than a full pattern, whether it's one or two, is equivalent,
and it only needs one day to uproot it. Okay. תניא כוותיה
דרב פפא, Tanya kevateih deRav Papa, we taught like רב פפא. Rav
Papa. Now this this case is a little bit confusing. היתה למודה
להיות רואה יום עשרים, hayta lemuda lihyot ro'a yom esrim, a woman
regularly saw on day 20. ושינתה ליום שלשים, veshinta leyom sheloshim, and
now she's seeing on day 30. So that's month number one, she
saw on day 30. זה וזה אסורין, zeh vezeh asurin, so now
both 30 and 20 are a problem. 20's established and 30 is
the most recent month. הגיע יום עשרים ולא ראתה, higia yom esrim
velo ra'ata, now month number two, she didn't see on day 20.
מותרת לשמש עד יום שלשים, muteret leshamesh ad yom sheloshim, so she
can have sex until day 30, right? Because she only worries about
those particular points, not about the time in between. וחוששת ליום שלשים,
vechosheshet leyom sheloshim, but day 30 she's not going to have sex
because that might be the new one that's asserting itself. הגיע יום
שלשים וראתה, higia yom sheloshim vera'ata, and now on month number two,
she saw on day 30. So what happened? Month one she saw
on day 30 only, month two she saw on day 30 only.
Okay, so now we've had the new one assert itself twice in
a row. Yes? Clear? Okay, now וחוששת ליום שלשים, vechosheshet leyom sheloshim,
next month, day month three, she's going to also be worried for
it, both 20 and 30. הגיע יום עשרים ולא ראתה, higia yom
esrim velo ra'ata, come month three and she didn't see on day
20, okay? הגיע יום שלשים ולא ראתה, higia yom sheloshim velo ra'ata,
and now she didn't see on day 30 either. We were just
on the cusp of establishing 30, right? Because it was month three,
she didn't see 20, but she didn't see 30 either. Then הגיע
יום עשרים וראתה. higia yom esrim vera'ata. Then month four came and
she saw on day 20. Now of course your question's going to
be to me, how could she see on day 20 on month
four if she didn't see before, the gap is growing, it's not
a 30-day gap, it's a big so again we're talking we have
to be talking about day of the month, not day of the
gap. You you see why. So anyway, month three was a total
miss, and now day four she reasserted, month four, excuse me, she
reasserted 20. So what is the הלכה? halacha? הותרה יום שלשים, hutra
yom sheloshim, goodbye יום שלשים. yom sheloshim. ונעשה יום עשרים, vena'aseh yom
esrim, and day 20 is now re-establishes itself מפני שאורח בזמנו בא,
mipnei she'oreach bizmano ba, because the guest comes in its time. The
visitor comes at its expected time. The visitor. Right? Some women call
the period their monthly visitor. The visitor comes at its expected time.
So therefore it's not, right, some Jewish thing. Anyway, so therefore month
twenty reasserts. Now how—so there's a couple of interesting things to point
out about this. First of all, how is this like רב פפא?
Rav Pappa? It's like רב פפא Rav Pappa because you had two
months of day thirty, and even though you had it twice, it
got uprooted just by having twenty reassert itself. So there you see
even two months running of the new thing, it gets uprooted once.
The problem is that's not such a good proof for רב פפא,
Rav Pappa, right? Because why is that not a good proof? You
see, you had two thirties and then all you needed was one
twenty to get rid of it. Why is that not a good
proof for רב פפא? Rav Pappa? Third month you didn't have thirty
yet? Third month you had nothing. Right. So that's—so okay, so number
one, you also have the fact that it didn't happen for a
month altogether. But more than that, the—it got—thirty got dismissed because twenty
reasserted itself, because the וסת קבוע vesset kavua that reasserted itself. What
if you had thirty, thirty, and twenty-eight? Would it be so clear
that thirty got dismissed? Right? Here, one of the things that gets
thirty off the table is that you have the powerhouse of twenty,
the וסת קבוע vesset kavua that reasserts itself. Dov's making a face.
He doesn't think that should matter. But it certainly is something that's
different. Let me point out another thing that's different about this. Okay?
Here's an interesting question, what I've been asking you. Can you have
an established וסת vesset. uprooted if it's missed three times without being
replaced? Well, you actually have this in the scenario. Month one was
thirty, month two was thirty, month three was zero. Does that uproot
twenty or not? It sounds like no, because it says month forty—month
four, excuse me, you had twenty assert itself and now it reasserts.
So does that prove that three misses don't uproot? Or maybe this
is a special case because nothing happened instead, and the next thing
that did happen was the twenty. So again, we're left with a
lot of uncertainty about these issues. Who says that then, I mean?
Anything you can think of as a question here is a מחלוקת
ראשונים. machlokes rishonim. Okay. So anyway, we're left with a lot of
uncertainty. And one of these questions as I said is, do you
uproot a וסת קבוע vesset kavua by just missing three times or
does it actually have to be replaced? The general sense is that
it actually has to be replaced. Missing three times is not enough,
but that is—it's replaced by something else, right? By something else. Right.
Exactly. But anyway, but that is—but but, you know whatever, all that
stuff is debated. What's agreed upon, I mean? No. All right, let's
take a look now at the next—I should also say before we
move on, and now we are going to move on from וסתות,
vestos that the big—this is extremely relevant for us because now that
we've introduced a וסת הגוף which interestingly gets almost footnoted in brackets,
but a וסת הימים and a וסת החודש, we say nowadays women,
although all of these cases were a woman with a וסת קבוע
vesset kavua and being concerned when it's shifting, maybe it's shifting to
do this new thing. And you will notice by the way that
all these cases only had a woman being concerned about her established
and the most recent month. Right? And only the—and what she was
concerned about of the most recent month was a function of the
genre that her established וסת was. If her established וסת was a
gap, and then it went off, she's concerned about the gap variation.
If her established וסת was a חודש and she was off, then
she's assumed—concerned the next month about her established חודש and the new
חודש. But what we wind up doing is taking both of those
things, חודש and הפלגה, haflaga, which is called the space—I call it
ימים yamim but it's called הפלגה haflaga later—the spacing, and say that
even with a woman וסת שאינה קבועה, vesset she'eina kavua, she has
to be concerned the next month with both possible variations. So a
woman bleeds one day after twenty-five days and she bleeds on ראש
חודש, so the next—and she has no established pattern, then the coming
month she'll have to both not have sex on ראש חודש because
of the חודש genre, and on twenty-five days from the last time
she saw. Okay. Those—and we actually even insert a third one, which
we call a וסת בינונית—an vesset beinonit עונה בינונית, onah beinonit, a
standard one of a thirty-day gap regardless of when the last time
you saw. So that leads to this idea that a woman without
a וסת קבוע vesset kavua will often have to be concerned with
maybe up to three times for the following month. None of that
was clear in the גמרא Gemara that we just read. The גמרא
Gemara we just read was all about a woman with a וסת
קבוע vesset kavua and all about being concerned about based on the
same genre that she had established her וסת. But based on that
discussion leads to a whole sort of, you know, sort of complex
of הלכות halachos around וסתות and וסת שאינה קבועה. vesset she'eina kavua.
And actually I was just—my—דבורה, Dvorah, my wife was just teaching a
כלה last night in the house, and she was going through all
the calendars and how to figure it out and she said, "Now
you figure it out, so what would that be the next month?"
and going through all the different three things and a day or
night and the whole thing. Anyway, and then I said, "You know,
you can get an iPhone app to do this." And you really
can. Go on to your iPhone—your App Store, type in וסתות or
מקוה, Mikvah, and you will find an app that figures it out
all for you. Okay. Anyway, is this מאיר, Meir, the one that
said that אשה שאין לה וסת אסורה לשמש עם בעלה? ishah she'ein
lah vesset asurah l'shamesh im ba'alah? Yeah, but we don't—ברוך השם. Baruch
Hashem. Okay. Now, now this last משנה mishna really begins in the
beginning of the next פרק. perek. The iPhone goes blank when you
push it. Exactly. Anyway. Right, so now this משנה mishna knows. The
good thing about it is, I don't know if the app does
it, but if it also links into your calendar and gives you
reminders, you know, gives you the beep or the reminders. Oh, I
forgot, you have the GPS on it, it points you to the
nearest מקוה. mikvah. You can develop it. Good luck! Now we need
a שבת Shabbos phone. Yeah, okay. Anyway, okay. So now this next
משנה mishna gets to the discussion about דם בתולים, dam betulim, about
hymenal bleeding and that in the times of the משנה, mishna, that
was a reason that for a woman to not be a נדה,
niddah, that if soon after she had sex for the first time,
if she bled she could assume it was hymenal and that it
was basically דם מכה dam makka based on a wound, not based
on menstrual bleeding. She wouldn't be a נדה, niddah, as we will
see, not today but tomorrow, that evolved to a position even in
the גמרא Gemara and certainly post the גמרא Gemara. where the hymenal
bleeding is considered as if it were דם נדה dam niddah and
it makes a woman a נדה. niddah. But in the משנה, mishna,
it's a reason to make her not a נדה. niddah. And interestingly,
that is the last משנה mishna here. I can't explain in נדה
Niddah the way things are organized and the way פרקים prakim are
broken up. This משנה mishna really belongs in the beginning of the
next פרק. perek. Let's take a look. נשים בבתוליהן כגפנים, Nashim bivtuleihem
kegefanim, women in terms of their hymen, it's like vines. In what
way? They're not all the same. יש גפן שיינה אדום, Yesh gefen
sheyeina adom, there are some vines that the wine that comes from
it is red. ויש גפן שיינה שחור Veyesh gefen sheyeina shachor and
sometimes it's black. I assume that's just a function of the grapes,
right? I guess that's the point. ויש גפן שיינה מרובה, Veyesh gefen
sheyeina merube, sometimes there's a lot of juice in the grapes. ויש
גפן שיינה מועט Veyesh gefen sheyeina muat and some types of vines
has very little wine that comes from them. רבי יהודה אומר: Rabbi
Yehuda omer: כל גפן יש בה יין, Kol gefen yesh ba yayin,
all vines have wine, okay? ושאין בה יין הרי זו דורקטי, Veshein
ba yayin harei zu dorkati, which I'm sure is some Greek word
which the גמרא Gemara is going to, I didn't look up, but
probably means it's some type of a bad thing. Do we know
דורקטי? dorkati? We know דורקטי dorkati is children. It's a woman they
had family with the women were infertile. Right. For ArtScroll it is,
in Greek it is truchi and it actually appears in ירושלמי Yerushalmi
as דור קטוע dor katea changed to דורקטי. dorkati. Okay. What does
it mean? Dry. In Greek it is a dried-up vine. Oh, no,
it's a type of grape that just... it's a type of grape
that doesn't have much juice. Okay. Well that makes a lot of
sense. Okay. What was he trying to say, רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda?
Well, what's the whole משנה mishna trying to say? So let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara תנא: Tana: דור קטוע. dor katua.
So the גמרא Gemara does what it often does which is an
Aramaic etymology of a Greek word. So דורקטי dorkati as דור קטוע,
dor katua, a cut off generation. What does it mean? It's going
to say that what that means is that the גמרא understood that
if you have not so much hymenal bleeding, it's a sign that,
the גמרא's understanding was that women's menstrual blood was important somehow in
fertility, even though obviously you weren't having sex during menstruation. And somehow
also understood that that was being linked to hymenal bleeding and that's
how it's reading רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda statement. תני רבי חייא: Tani
Rabbi Chiya: כשם שהשאור יפה לעיסה, Keshem shehase'or yafe la'issa, the same
way sourdough is good for dough, כך דמים יפים לאשה, kach damim
yafim la'isha, blood is good for a woman presumably for fertility. You
know, the same way obviously you understand the metaphor, you know, the
sourdough causes the dough to puff up, so it's like the pregnancy
idea. תני משום רבי מאיר: Tani mishum Rabbi Meir: כל אשה שדמיה
מרובים בניה מרובים, Kol isha shedameha merubim baneha merubim, a woman who
has a lot of blood has a lot of children. So this
presumably is about menstrual blood and then you understand, I mean, don't
agree with the science, but you understand how they assumed it was
a regular part of the woman's body and it could have an
impact on fertility. But it seems the גמרא suggesting it's also linked
to the hymenal bleeding which seems particularly strange. Anyway, it's not נשים
בבתוליהן Nashim bivtuleihem as of the first time, one who hasn't bled
before, a menstrual bleed before. You mean נשים בבתוליהן Nashim bivtuleihem means
their bleeding that they're doing before they've had sex when they're younger?
Maybe. But the reason I'm skeptical is what the heck is this
משנה mishna doing anyway? And it seems as we'll read the next
פרק perek what it's doing here is that the next משנה mishna
is going to be a discussion about how long can a woman
assume that bleeding after the first time she's had sex is based
on hymenal bleeding. And so it makes sense to put out there,
look, not all women are the same, some women bleed a lot,
some women don't bleed a lot. So that's going to be an
interesting thing to be thinking about if we're going to try to
attribute bleeding to hymenal bleeding, acknowledging that there's a variation among women.
Okay. They don't say the same about men? I mean, he's saying
here... No. I mean you would think it would say that women
that have a lot of... a lot of seminal emission would be
good fertility, yeah, but they don't say that. Yeah, again, an excellent
point that it's focusing on the woman and hers being the cause,
her fault. Yep. I've had enough of you. Yeah, it's a very
good point. Look, I even remember recently, I'm sure you know more
cases, about cases in like a בית דין beis din in Israel,
I mean not so long ago, maybe 10 years ago, but I'm
sure they've had even more recent, that basically a couple wasn't having
kids and... it was, tests showed that it was the husband who
was sterile, but nevertheless somehow the בית דין Beit Din ruled that
the wife could be divorced without a כתובה Ketubah because it was
clearly, you know, just this is why people stop becoming frum. Seriously,
this is ridiculous. That case that I sent around where the chief
of the Jerusalem בית דין, Beit Din, the הרב אליהו, Rav Eliyahu,
had the פילגש pilegesh case. Take a פילגש pilegesh if the wife
didn't have children. Right, right. But that's a different question because that
could be the wife actually is sterile, you know, but but this
is the question about always assuming it could be. Right, right, right.
You're absolutely right. Alright, so now we move on. Other הלכות אישה?
halachot isha? No, other than I think I think it's just giving
context to the next משנה mishnah where we're going to say that
how long can you assume a time of bleeding to acknowledge that
there's a change, it depends, that there's a variation amongst women. Let's
take a look at the next משנה. mishnah. תינוקת שלא הגיע זמנה
לראות ונישאת. Tinoket shelo higia zemana lirot veniset. If a תינוקת, tinoket,
notice that phrase, a baby literally, a very young girl who is
not yet under, prepubescent girl, שלא הגיע זמנה, shelo higia zemana, it's
not of the age of having her period, and she gets married.
And obviously she's having sex. Not קידושין, kiddushin, נישואין, nisuin, which means
that she's living with her husband and having sex. So, and then
her hymen breaks. How long can you assume any bleeding is hymenal?
So the assumption here is not because she's young there's going to
be more hymenal bleeding, but because there's less of a reason to
assume that it's menstrual bleeding. So therefore it's much more you're much
more prepared to attribute any bleeding to the hymenal bleeding. She's a
little girl. She's a little girl and he basically raped her. Right,
right. I mean, you know. Well, תינוקת. tinoket. Yes, right. Definitely under
12 years old. בית שמאי אומרים נותנין לה ארבע לילות. Beit Shammai
omrim notnin lah arba leilot. So בית שמאי Beit Shammai says she
has four nights. For the next four nights if there's bleeding you
can assume it's hymenal, after that no. בית הלל, Beit Hillel, yes.
Yes, yes. ובית הלל אומרים עד שתחיה המכה. U-Veit Hillel omrim ad
she-tichyeh ha-makkah. No, until you have evidence that the wound healed. It
could be much more than four. So how do you know if
the wound healed? So we'll discuss that in the גמרא. So they're
saying it's a מכה. makkah. The the hymenal bleeding, yes. Not because
she's underage. They would call it a מכה makkah even if she's
an adult as long as it's not, it's not uterine bleeding. It's
bleeding based on something having ruptured. Because if it's a תינוקת tinoket
because then it's clear, it's much more obvious that there's no concern
about uterine bleeding because she doesn't... So they're really talking about a
very young girl. Right, under 12, under prepubescent. Could be younger, but
minimally prepubescent. Age of puberty has varied a lot over time. All
right. הגיע זמנה לראות ונישאת. Higia zemana lirot veniset. Now she's hit
puberty and she's married. All right, but she has not yet had
her period but she's hit puberty. בית שמאי אומרים נותנין לה לילה
הראשון. Beit Shammai omrim notnin lah laylah ha-rishon. So therefore she's hit
puberty, after the first night I'm going to be concerned that any
bleeding is uterine bleeding. ובית הלל אומרים עד מוצאי שבת ארבע לילות.
U-Veit Hillel omrim ad Motzaei Shabbat arba leilot. No, that case like
בית הלל Beit Hillel is always one more lenient than בית שמאי.
Beit Shammai. So at last case בית שמאי Beit Shammai said four,
this case בית הלל Beit Hillel says four. I'll give her four
nights until מוצאי שבת. Motzaei Shabbat. What does that mean? Because the
first משנה כתובות mishnah Ketubot says that women got married on Wednesday.
First time they're having sex is Wednesday night. Wednesday night, Thursday night,
Friday night, Saturday night. So I give her four nights until מוצאי
שבת, Motzaei Shabbat, any bleeding there I will attribute to the hymenal
bleeding. So the גמרא will ask: נותנין לה ארבע לילות? notnin lah
arba leilot? So the גמרא will ask. ראתה ועודנה בבית אביה. Ra-atah
ve-odennah be-veit aviha. Now let's say not only is she hit puberty,
but she actually has had her period, maybe just once, but she's
had her period. So then it's obviously much, you know, then you
have to be concerned about about uterine bleeding. בית שמאי אומרים נותנין
לה בעילת מצווה. Beit Shammai omrim notnin lah beilat mitzvah. I will
only allow the act of the original act of sex. Interesting called
בעילת מצווה, beilat mitzvah, why מצווה mitzvah here? We'll talk about that
maybe a little later. But anyway, the first act of sex, there
I will say the bleeding is hymenal bleeding, but any bleeding afterwards
is going to be a problem. ובית הלל אומרים כל הלילה כולה.
U-Veit Hillel omrim kol ha-laylah kullah. No, the entire night and they
could have sex multiple times in that night and she could bleed
during that night. Any bleeding during that first night is attributed to
hymenal bleeding; after that, it's a problem. Now there's a little bit
of a confusion, not confusion, a little unclear about whether we mean
bleeding that occurs only during the act of sex itself, or can
sometimes bleeding that occurred later be still attributed to the hymenal bleeding?
Based on an earlier גמרא and based on what we'll see, there
seems to be that at least in some cases that if they
had sex and there was bleeding, then for the entire next day
any bleeding, even that occurs you know without intercourse, can be attributed
to that bleeding that occurred the previous night. Okay, so that's not
spelled out here in the משנה. mishnah. Let's move on quickly because
we just have... yeah, go ahead, there's a quick point. Why is
having sex with a prepubescent girl not זרע לבטלה? zera levatala? Well,
the same reason, look, there's obviously as you point out things that
are a lot worse here than זרע לבטלה, zera levatala, but the
same reason that having sex with your a man having sex with
his pregnant wife or his postmenopausal wife is not זרע לבטלה. zera
levatala. Basically, any act of marital sex, it it does not have
to have the possibility of procreation to make it not זרע לבטלה.
zera levatala. Because the גמרא basically understands that that is a that
that I mean look, that gets into a much larger and important
discussion about the... is marital sex only somehow redeemed and justified in
the context of leading to procreation, or is it an intrinsic good
of connecting of husband and wife, like and so on. Okay, so
that gets back to your other point that it's what type of
real relationship is going on here. I understand. Alright, let's take a
look at the גמרא. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק Amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak בפירוסא, B'firusa, when we say prepubescent that it has four
nights or until it's healed, that's even if she had her period,
meaning it's about the age. So if she's under age even if
for one bizarre reason she did have some bleeding once, but if
it was very unexpected, that doesn't change her status. ממי, Mimay, how
do you know? מדקאי מתני בסיפא Me-dekai matni ba-seifa בין רסתה בין
שלא רסתה, Bein rasta bein shelo rasta, because since it gives distinct
categories in the end by a girl that's hit puberty, whether she's
had her period or not, מכלל דרישא, M'klal d'reisha, the beginning where
it said prepubescent, לא שנא הכי ולא שנא הכי. Lo shna hachi
v'lo shna hachi. It doesn't matter whether she's actually had a period
or not, if she's under the age that we consider that a
bizarre occurrence and it does not change her status. תניא נמי הכי
Tanya nami hachi ובית הלל אומרים עד שתחיה המכה U'Beit Hillel omrim
ad she-tichye ha-macha until the wound heals, בין רסתה בין לא רסתה,
Bein rasta bein lo rasta, whether she actually has has had a
period or not, if she's prepuberty, it all has the same status.
Now, עד שתחיה המכה, Ad she-tichye ha-macha, how do you determine when
the wound is healed for בית הלל? Beit Hillel? It's very open-ended.
So עד כמה, Ad kamma, when do you know this? אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav כל זמן שנוחרת, Kol
zman she-nocheret, as long as she is נוחרת, nocheret, נוחרת nocheret sort
of means like stabbed, here it means somehow like bleeding as a
result of the wound. Well, okay, thank you, that was the question.
So let's see what the גמרא says. כי אמריתה קמיה דשמואל, Ki
amrisa kammai d'Shmuel, when I said in front of שמואל, Shmuel, אמר
רב יהודה Amar Rav Yehuda presumably said, when I said this over
in front of שמואל, Shmuel, because רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was both
the student of רב Rav and of שמואל, Shmuel, אמר לי, Amar
li, he said to me, נחירותא זו איני יודע מה היא, Nechiruta
zo eini yodea ma hi, I don't know what this נחירותא nechiruta
means. אלא, Ela, here's what, here's the הלכה. halacha. כל זמן שהרוק
מצרי בתוך הפה מחמת תשמיש, Kol zman she-ha-rok matzri b'toch ha-peh machamat
tashmish, using obviously a metaphor here. As long as the spit is
in the mouth because of sex. Which means as long as there
is blood that comes during the act of sex, then that is
an evidence that the wound has not healed, that there's still hymenal
bleeding, and then as תוספות points out, any bleeding that will occur
for the next day can also be attributed to the hymenal bleeding.
So the evidence that there is still it is still hymenal bleeding
is that whenever there is sex, there is blood. So the גמרא
says נחירותא דרב דקאמר רב היכי דמי? Nechiruta d'Rav d'ka amar Rav
heichi dami? So how about when רב Rav said נחירותא, nechiruta, what
does he mean? What would be how would that be indicated? So
אמר שמואל אמר רב יצחק Amar Shmuel amar Rav Yitzchak לדידי פירשה
לי מיניה דרב, L'didmi parsha li minei d'Rav, according to me here's
how רב's Rav position was explained. עומדת ורואה יושבת ואינה רואה. Omedet
v'roah, yoshevet v'eina roah. When she stands, she sees, she bleeds, but
when she sits, she doesn't bleed. So standing is presumably somehow more
discomforting or maybe more irritating to the to the hymen. So בידוע
שלא חיה המכה, Biyaduah she-lo chaya hamacha, then you can say ah
look, since it's coming only when she stands, not when she sits,
that shows that it's coming from the hymen. And that somehow the
גמרא understood would have been some exacerbated by standing. על גבי קרקע
ורואה, Al gabei karka v'roah, it's clear the next case. When she's
sitting on hard ground she's bleeding. על גבי כרים וכסתות ואינה רואה,
Al gabei karim u'chsasot v'eina roah, if she's sitting on pillows, not.
So somehow the discomfort is causing irritation that indicates hymenal bleeding. בידוע
שלא חיה המכה. Biyaduah she-lo chaya hamacha. And presumably if it indicates
hymenal bleeding, not only is this bleeding okay, but maybe presumably bleeding
during sex is okay. It's again, it's not clear how much does
that then translate to other occurrences as well. Okay, now if x,
where am I? על גבי כולם ורואה ועל גבי כולם ואינה רואה,
Al gabei kulam v'roah v'al gabei kulam v'eina roah, however if there's
no difference, if whether standing or sitting, hard ground or soft ground,
she consistently sees or doesn't see. In those cases, בידוע שחיה המכה,
Biyaduah she-chaya hamacha, you know that it's healed. You don't really know
it's healed, but תוספות says you don't have evidence that it hasn't
healed. So you have to be concerned that it healed. You don't
have good evidence. So basically if she's bleeding all the time you
think it has healed? Why would you think? Because maybe now it's
her period. So meaning what שמואל Shmuel says is, all I need
for evidence that it's still a problem is that bleeding during sex.
רב Rav says, now it's not exactly clear does רב agree with
שמואל Shmuel and is he adding, is he independent of שמואל, Shmuel,
but anyway so תוספות thinks that he's being more strict. In addition
to bleeding during sex, I need other supporting evidence and I need
to see that in other ways certain things are causing bleeding and
other things not. So that's much stricter than שמואל. Shmuel. Okay, now
that is a very the case about an underage girl. I mean
underage, even the even the second case is that she could be
12 years old. הגיע זמנה לירוס. Higia zmana l'iros. Now she's hit
puberty, so and she hasn't yet had her period. So there בית
שמאי Beit Shammai says the night and בית הלל Beit Hillel says
four nights. איתמר, Itmar, so we talk. שימשה בימים, Shimsha b'yamim, let's
say you said four nights, let's say she's had sex during the
day or whatever, exactly. רב אמר לא הפסידה לילות. Rav amar lo
hifsida leilot. Fine, so we don't mean literally four nights, we mean
over the period of four days. So she didn't lose the nights
and if she has sex at night as well and she bleeds
at night it's also not a problem. ולוי אמר הפסידה לילות. V'Levi
amar hifsida leilot. No, she lost the nights. So presumably it's like
you know... If sex four times, and if it's more than four
times then it's a problem, even if it's within the period of
four days. That seems to be the point, anyway. It's as the
גמרא *Gemara* says, ולוי אמר הפסידה לילות *VeLevi amar hisida leilot*. מאי
ארבע לילות דקתני *Mai arba leilot diktani*? When we say ארבע לילות
*arba leilot*, we mean ארבע עונות *arba onot*. We mean four periods.
So רב אמר *Rav amar*, I'm going back a couple lines, רב
אמר לא הפסידה לילות *Rav amar lo hisida leilot*. עד מוצאי שבת
תנן *Ad Motzei Shabbos tnan*. We say until מוצאי שבת *Motzei Shabbos*,
which we mean is you have, you know, four 24-hour days, and
any sex and bleeding that occurs during that time is not a
problem. ולוי אמר הפסידה לילות *VeLevi amar hisida leilot*. She lost the
nights. מאי ארבע לילות דקתני *Mai arba leilot diktani*? ארבע עונות *Arba
onot*. We mean four units. Remember, we call either daytime or nighttime
a unit. So what לוי *Levi* says is any bleeding that occurs
during four units of time that comes with sex is not a
problem. So if it's a night, a day, a night, and a
day, those you've used up your four units. Right, but no, presumably,
no, you can do multiple times during a unit. You can. Right.
It was only לוי *Levi* that we say only one act of
sex, but still, it's all within one unit. You've got four units
to use over this eight, over this four-day period, over the period
with eight units in it. And after your four units are used
up, whether there was bleeding during sex, any other bleeding... exactly. It
seems to be. Okay. So לרב למה לי למיתני ארבע לילות *LeRav
lama li lemitni arba leilot*? Why does it say four nights if
it's really about four days? אורחא דמילתא קא משמע לן דאורחא דביאה
בלילה *Orcha demilta ka mashma lan de'orcha deviah belailah*. Yeah, because normally
when we're talking about sex, we're talking about night. And as we
know, you know, there's other גמרות *Gemaros* that say you're not allowed
to have sex during the day unless under special circumstances. וללוי ליתני
ארבע עונות *UleLevi lemitni arba onot*. So according to לוי *Levi*, we
get why it says four nights. עד מוצאי שבת למה לי *Ad
Motzei Shabbos lama li*? Why does it say until מוצאי שבת *Motzei
Shabbos*, which suggests four 24-hour days? הא קא משמע לן *Ha ka
mashma lan*. It's teaching me דשרי למיבעל לכתחילה בשבת *deshari lemivaal lechatchilah
beShabbos*. It wanted to emphasize that it's through מוצאי שבת *Motzei Shabbos*,
because if it's through מוצאי שבת *Motzei Shabbos*, it's including שבת *Shabbos*.
And therefore it's basically saying that you're having sex on שבת *Shabbos*.
Okay. Now why would I have thought that's a problem? So anybody
who learned the beginning of כתובות *Ketubot* knows there's a big question
of are you allowed to have sex for the first time on
שבת *Shabbos*. Is the rupturing of the hymen a problem or not?
Now here it causes bleeding and so on. Is it a שבת
*Shabbos* עמנא *amana*? The general conclusion in the גמרא *Gemara* is no.
Here it's a little bit less of an issue because here they've
already been having sex before שבת *Shabbos* and there's been some bleeding.
There's just been ongoing bleeding. So maybe the fact that there was
bleeding before makes it even less of an issue. But nevertheless, says
לוי *Levi*, it's important to say that you can have sex on
שבת *Shabbos* even though it might continue to cause bleeding. Okay. כדשמואל
*KiShmuel*. Like שמואל *Shmuel*. דאמר שמואל *Damar Shmuel*, פרצה דחוקה *pirtcha dechuka*.
Remember how much we dealt with house metaphors by women like בית
*bayis* and עליה *aliya* and all of that? So this imagery of
שמואל *Shmuel* is very similar. He says, I'll say it literally, if
you have a tight opening in a door or like in a
fence, מותר ליכנס בה בשבת *mutar leikanes bah beShabbos*. You can, you
know, sort of enter in on שבת *Shabbos*. Imagine it's like a
stone fence. אף על פי שמשיר צרורות *af al pi shemeshir tzerorot*,
even though in squeezing in it causes some pebbles to dislodge. Okay,
that's the metaphor. So I think you get the point. So שמואל
*Shmuel* says... No, I think pedophilia... Wait, wait, we're not here about
pedophilia. It's you have this... you're hurting her... but this is about
שבת *Shabbos*. This is about שבת *Shabbos*. This could be about adults.
This is a משנה *Mishna* of תינוקות *tinokos*. Okay, all right. גירסא
*Girsa*, I agree, that's a problem. But this context is bracketing the
child out. This context is... doesn't matter how old the woman is.
Well, in the case you're right, she is, you know, recently hit
puberty. It's true. Fighting his way in is what it's saying and
it's okay. Yes. But it could be even a non-child. It's not...
it's because it's the first time the woman's had sex, the first
few times. Right. So the point here is is that given that
it's a... that even though they had sex before, so it's not
like it's going to create rupture the hymen the first time, but
it's still going to cause bleeding. Nevertheless, you're allowed to continue to
have sex on שבת *Shabbos* even though it will continue to tear
the hymen and continue to cause bleeding and pain. Right. איתמר *Itmar*.
It was taught. So that's the purpose why we emphasized that it
went through שבת *Shabbos*. So let's just read one more line in
this. בעל ולא מצא דם וחזר ובעל ומצא דם *Baal velo matza
dam vechazar ubaal umatza dam*. You know what? Actually, no, let's stop
here. Okay. So we'll pick up at דף *daf*...